in this video I would like to tell you
the reasons why I think this year 2023
should be the year when you finally
learn flutter first I would like to sell
you flutter a little bit and tell you
the reasons why I think learning it is a
great way to invest your time then
because I want to be intellectually
honest with you we are going to see some
of the shortcomings the framework has
because everything has its trade-offs
when working with flutter we have to
make some compromises and we're going to
see what they are and finally I am going
to tell you what is the number one
biggest mistake that people make when
learning flutter and how to avoid it if
you're ready I'm ready let's get started
flutter if you don't know what it is is
a framework made by Google that allows
developers to build multi-platform
applications using only one programming
language when I first tried flutter back
in 2018
multi-platform and IOS and Android but
the flutter team did not stop there and
now multi-platform means iOS
Android Mac OS Linux windows web and
embedded devices that is an incredible
value proposition especially for people
that like to build things for makers and
entrepreneurs that want to be able to
build prototypes and test ideas on
multiple platforms as quick as possible
being able to build something for all of
these platforms using only one framework
and one programming language gives
creative people an incredible power
flutter is a force multiplier now
flutter is the framework Dart is the
programming language zart has a great
developer experience and is incredibly
easy to learn if you already know
JavaScript Java kotlin and even c-sharp
the cool thing about Dart and flutter is
that because they're both Google
products their teams can work very close
to each other this is great because that
means that when flutter needs a feature
and dart doesn't have that feature the
Dark theme can just build it for them
for for example initially Dart did not
have ahead of time compilation but now
it does because flutter needed it to
produce faster apps other Frameworks
usually don't have this Advantage they
don't have this level of influence over
the language and the virtual machine
they use but Slaughter thus the
developer experience in flutter is also
something to highlight developer tools
of the framework are almost at the same
level with Native development on
developer tools flutter blows react
native out of the water on the
commercial side many big companies are
betting heavily on flutter from BMW to
byte dance tencent eBay new bank Toyota
and even Google themselves they
literally rewrote the Google pay app
used by millions of users from scratch
with flutter the new app has 35 percent
less lines of code down to 1.1 million
from 1.7 million and they estimate that
they have saved between 60 and 70
percent of the engineers time this shows
you the commitment and trust that Google
has on the framework and it eases the
fears of lots of people including me
that thought maybe Google was going to
kill Slaughter the way it kills many of
its products because I know I make it
sound like Florida is the perfect
framework let's now talk about the
issues it has because if something is
too good to be true it probably is at
the end of the day flutter is a
cross-platform framework and just like
with the other cross-platform Frameworks
you won't have the same level of control
that you would have if you were building
a native app while building your app you
might find out that there are some
things the framework doesn't officially
support but from experience usually you
will be able to find a community made
plugin that does what you need this has
always been the case for me when working
with flutter because of how big and
active the community is but nevertheless
nothing compares to being able to use
the apis that the phone has directly
rather than trying to find Community
packages and hoping that they work and
that they are up to date The Wave
flutter works is by basically rendering
a canvas on the screen of the user and
painting the UI of the app using a
custom graphics engine which is what
makes flutter so cross-platform anywhere
it goes the framework paints a canvas
and builds its own UI but because of
these two things happen number one
flutter apps are a bit heavier than
normal apps because your app has to be
packaged and distributed with your code
plus the graphics engine code and number
two may or may not be a problem
depending on your goals if we take a
look at Apple music we can see that this
is an app that looks feels and smells
like apple it's using apple design
language buttons animations navigation
gestures Etc because as we said flutter
has its own Graphics engine flutter apps
can't use any of the host platforms UI
components you could recreate all the
Styles manually and try to make a button
that looks just like an iOS button or
you can use any of the pre-made
components that try to look like iOS but
they are not the real deal and it's easy
to notice so if you want to build apps
that look and feel native to the phone
and the host platform maybe flutter
isn't a good choice but this isn't a
problem and it's actually good news when
your app has a design language of its
own if we take a look at the Duolingo
for example or Tick Tock or grab or
waking up we can see that these apps are
apps that do not use the design language
of the platform they are in they have
custom made designs of their own and on
this floor excels with flutter you own
every pixel of the screen because you
are not bound to the constraints of the
platform you are in you can Implement
whatever crazy UI your designer made
like what you are looking at right now
that is an app built with flutter with a
very custom UI animations and gestures
created to showcase the new graphics
engine flutter is going to get so to
conclude the shortcomings of flutter are
the shortcomings of many other
cross-platform Frameworks that suffer
from a lack of official API support and
make us rely on not so stable community
plugin and also because of how flutter
is built our app won't be able to use
the UI components of the host platform
which depending on how you look at it it
might or may not be a good thing because
that gives us the chance to implement
our own custom UI at the end of the day
a cross platform app will always be a
guest on the phone and not a first class
citizen which may or may not be a deal
breaker for you depending on what your
app needs this is of course not a
complete list of the good and the bad of
the flutter framework and you should not
base your opinions on what people on the
internet say anyways before you read the
comments of people telling you how good
or bad flutter is just try it out and
evaluate it by yourself the framework is
so easy to learn the community and
documentation are so good that there
isn't a reason not to try it if you're
still watching and you want to learn
floater you need to avoid the mistake
many people including me make when
learning Slaughter and that is learning
flutter first because flutter sounds so
exciting people just go to the flutter
website or buy a flutter course and
start learning right away the problem
with doing that is that there's giving a
very important part and that is that
that is the language that powers flutter
and if you skip that completely and just
go and try to learn flutter you're still
going to learn Slaughter but your
progress will be very slow if you skip
Dart and jump straight into flutter when
you see flutter code for the first time
you won't know if this weird looking
code is weird because of the syntax of
dark or is it something related to
flutter itself I did this I jumped
straight to flutter without First
Learning at least the basics of dark and
because of this it took me a longer time
to be productive in floor than I would
like to admit this is why I created two
courses aimed at people that are
absolute flutter beginners the first
course is Dart 4 begins this is a free
2-hour course where we don't talk about
flutter we just write dark code we
learned the basics and we understand
what makes dark special and different
from other programming languages and we
learn the features of the language that
Slaughter uses the most it is not a full
guide into the dark language because
Dart is too big instead it is just a
guide that gives you exactly what you
need to feel comfortable when learning
flutter for the first time nothing else
and nothing more when you finish that
course you will be ready to jump into
the second course flutter for beginners
that is a free free free
seven hour course where you will go from
not knowing anything about flutter to
building three apps including a
productivity app and a webtoon discovery
app we will learn how to build uis with
flutter interactivity widgets life
cycles data fetching navigation and more
you can enroll to both courses right now
for free all you have to do is click the
link below that's it for this video
thank you for watching in 2022 I wish
you a normal Hamburg Khan
2023o see you on the next one bye